and there i have
many different they have many different
questions i don't know even if we'll get
to them all today i don't know how much
time you help us
um one
one question which i had asked on
youtube maybe we could start with that
was about the
the term peripheral awareness so
um basically like i had
i read your essay about it and i
listened to a couple of videos
but basically whenever you whenever you
start talking about peripheral
or awareness i would get a little bit um
confused because the word is not like it
would work it can
be interpreted different ways so i was
trying to understand
exactly what it means the
peripheral awareness and
what i had what i had asked and when i
wrote on youtube i basically kind of
tried to describe how i was
understanding it so that you could
tell me if it was correct or not
um and how i how i had kind of what i
had gathered from it was that it's
basically like let's say if i'm sitting here
like let's say if i'm sitting here
talking to you on the chair
example you talk about being having
peripheral awareness
with the reference point of sitting so
example i'm sitting
here talking to you on the chair
formulating my question and figuring out
how to put it well and i should have
like a
kind of background awareness of the fact
that i'm sitting
for example um
well sort of you know just maybe before
we get
too far into it uh it's not necessarily
like you must have it
in a sense of i must make this effort
and maintain this background
you just need to recognize it as that
which is already there
that's in those talks i think i was i
was when i was describing peripheral
awareness i ended up talking about the
knowledge which is already peripheral in its
which is already peripheral in its
nature so you already know you're seated
you already know the door is closed you
already know uh you're talking to me so
all these things are already there
so that's why and you're not attending
them you don't need to keep telling to
yourself while you're talking to me that you are
while you're talking to me that you are
seated you are seated but if i were to
ask in the middle of your sentence
about something different are you seated
you would immediately have the answer
which means that knowledge is already
there without
not not being required to be to be
directly attended
so it's peripheral yeah so peripheral
awareness will be basically the
recognition of that which you already
know there which is the basis of your
situation um so it's it's subtler because
um so it's it's subtler because
often yes people would kind of hear it
and then immediately
ah peripheral awareness is something i
must do in this peripheral manner
but then they end up still in the same
sense trying to attend to it
but as i said so then what's uh gone
no i was just gonna say so instead of
attending to oh i'm seated i'm seated
you just want to recognize the level of
that knowledge and not keep having to
answer it to yourself because you
already know the answer
um okay so then but like what would be
the difference between
like somebody who is practicing
practicing peripheral awareness or kind
of working on it is something you still
have to work on if i understand well
it's like not because otherwise
what i'm trying to understand is the
difference between somebody practicing
for practicing mindfulness as you explain
practicing mindfulness as you explain
and somebody who's like a normal person
just going about their daily life who
also knows that the door is closed who
also knows that their seizure who also
knows that they're
yeah but they're not that they're
talking they're not aware of it
they know if they ask the question but
they don't have the awareness of their
knowledge persisting as a base of their
situation because if they did they would
because if they did they would
experience this passion they would not
be able to engage with sensual desires
and ill will yet they do
which means they don't have the right
knowledge like yes if they stop and ask
themselves they will know it
so it's not knowing that the door is
closed that you are seated
but it's being aware of the knowledge
that the door is closed and you are
seated while you are engaged with other things
while you are engaged with other things
so it's really the relationship between
the peripheral
and what you're choosing to attend to
and that's exactly why the mindfulness
is that framework the container
and and that's exactly what it is
developing not just
yeah i know i'm seated full stop i
completed the mindfulness no
is the relationship between your
knowledge that you are seated and what
you choose to do
intend speak think while you're seated
on the basis of that situation [Music]
[Music]
okay so he says okay it's the
relationship between the knowledge
that you are seated and the
and what you choose to do on the base of
that situation so now
okay so you're aware that you're seated
you know that you you know
like you're aware of that you know that
you are seated in the sense and
like so what uh my other kind of
question was so this
like this like knowing being aware of
being ceases
is basically you're basically aware of a
sensation right like being aware that
the no no no you're not your
no no no you're not your
like you don't need sensations for the
knowledge of your seated position
you have the knowledge which is why you
know what sensations to look for
so the knowledge comes first not the
sensations it's usually that expectation of your
it's usually that expectation of your
attention to find something more
substantial that needs to discern these sensations
that needs to discern these sensations
they would then be representation of the
seated but you already know you're seated you
but you already know you're seated you
can answer to me are you seated you
could give immediate answer
before you tap into your sensations of
seated body which is always secondary to
the knowledge that you are already
deceited so that's what i mean it's actually
so that's what i mean it's actually
subtler than just attending to the
sensations of
i don't know touching the chair or
something like that
it's the knowledge of it
but i know that i'm seated because i
chose to sit down like i like i chose to sit
to sit down like i like i chose to sit
down and now i am
now i'm seated yes and you don't need
sensations to confirm to you that what
you already know that you're seated
they're completely redundant actually
how did how your body feels and how the
chair really presses you and stuff
it's it's completely redundant you're
seated you and you said it yourself
you know you're seated because you chose
to sit down there were no sensations
involved in your choice of sitting down
it was like i want to sit down i need to
sit down it's better to sit down
all these other intentions yet when we
speak about it people think austin said
why would you bring the sensations into
it then when you realize
had nothing to do with neither your
decision nor the knowledge of being
seated i mean i know why because everybody does
i mean i know why because everybody does
that that's like the natural kind of
i must look closer at these sensations
or something as if some
somehow that analyzes more of you no you
see if you want to analyze the nature of
if you want to analyze the nature of
being seated as exactly as you did kind
of spontaneously
ah intention to sit down brought me here
which means
your intention to sit down is still
present there with you it wasn't half an
hour ago when you set
it remains enduring while you're seated
because if your intention to be seated
changes you will stand
up or lay down so
and that's another thing that i talked
about the level of intention yeah in the
relationship with those other in the
same peripheral awareness talks is that
knowing the intention why you want to
like oh i'm doing this and then knowing
that while you're doing it
your intention is persistently kind of
it's enduring there is a binding factor
you're not like going to
moment-to-moment awareness no the
knowledge of what you want to do
is the unifying factor of all of your
particular little actions
so the knowledge of what you're going to
do is basically the framework of your
current action if you want to be mindful
of it
okay so um if i try to kind of put it in
in language for
under six years old it would be like
yeah basically i know that i know that
i'm sitting down based on the fact that
i
that i had the intention to sit down and
it's like and that i and that i still choose
like and that i and that i still choose
to keep sitting down
this is like the main this is the first
thing that comes
like or the
so yeah because i agree i agree that
sensation like you don't need to take
that further in a sense
what do i do now like with this
knowledge of being seated
you just need to start using it as a
basis they will take away from being
self-centered with your point of view
towards what you attend to and see
whatever you choose to attend to on the
basis of this seated situation
that's what the buddha would say like
when he was still the bodhisattva in the
forest uh walking doing a walking meditation or
uh walking doing a walking meditation or
or something
and then he would say if there is like
an unwholesome state would arise in my
mind fear or something i would not change my
fear or something i would not change my
position
until i first dispelled the fear then if
i happen to be seated
and then there was lust or fear again i
wouldn't stand up until i dispel the
fear so he wouldn't change the basis of his
so he wouldn't change the basis of his
situation
because it would mean he acted out of
lust or fear or anything unwholesome
so he used the base of situation as an
enduring framework
container for whatever present
phenomenon has been kind of besetting
his mind
but without a base without the factual
basis of your situation such as your
body your body posture your currently
your body posture your currently
enduring feeling anything from sati
patana you will be engaged with the current
you will be engaged with the current
state of mind through your point of view
and that's exactly where that
self-centeredness and conceit get it
involves it's not like the people are choose to
it's not like the people are choose to
be conceited
they just don't know they have no other
reference point between them and what
they attend to
so the knowledge i'm describing it's not
like i need to clarify this knowledge
more in a sense of
get more details about it although that
can be helpful for somebody
it's more like now that i'm clear now
that i know it
i need to stop attending that and use it
as a basis for what i'm attending
and that's what i mean the relationship
between the two that then
eventually you develop that sufficiently
enough your sense of self the sense
the self-centered point of view that
chooses to attend and thinks it's the
receptor of these things that come to
your senses
will be made redundant and then it's
just as the buddha would say in saudi patana
as the buddha would say in saudi patana
oh he knows there is the presence of the
lustful mind that's the lustful mind
there is a non-lustful mind as a
non-loveful mind elated mind depressed
mind doesn't matter it's not like
i am depressed i am lustful i'm hateful
or something like that
yeah yeah like this by this i
this i understand like i agree
that yeah i think many people get this
part many people get this part from
satya patana
but what i'm trying to describe is the
only way to get it is to
establish the proper base of mindfulness
of the level of the knowledge
not on the level of kind of sensations
or something that i choose
i choose to attend as representative of
the seated position
which means still puts you in the center
the driving seat
yeah and yeah to say this i agree
but like i okay agree like
always because always the mind like
always people are just
like looking at what they see what they
hear what you
what you think what you are like what i
what i want what i don't want what i
feel what i so this like if you look
always outside this i see that if you're
just looking outside at the
objects of my my senses or object of my
like outside of my attention then this
is no good because it's just
i am i am seeing this i am hearing this
i am automatically as this
what i would add there is that even the
notion of sensations
is also another thing that's outside
outside to your self-centeredness
so the only thing that's behind the only
thing that's not
outside of your point of view not like
the where your attention can land is what's
where your attention can land is what's
peripheral to it which is the level of
the knowledge
you cannot make that into physical sense
like because that becomes something you can
because that becomes something you can
attend so even your body posture
is to be known as such not attended
and felt as often uh described in
contemporary sort of
you know buddhist teachings and so on
yeah so that's the that's the difference
between
yeah like i understand i i agree with
you about sensations and that was why i
was like kind of
doubtful about this uh kind of doubtful
about the
the idea of of it if it consists of some
sensations then then it's not correct
because you're just paying yeah you're
just paying attention to something
that's like
in theory outside of you yeah there's no
wisdom that can
arise from there and wisdom is like as
you say it has to be on the level of
what knows the thing that the thing that
knows like the
the wisdom comes from the from basically
completely bypassing and extinguishing that
bypassing and extinguishing that
self-centered
point of view when as i said your sense
of self
is made redundant like you just know the
bodies as such feelings as such uh thoughts are
as such feelings as such uh thoughts are
as
are as such and so on so there is no
like oh i am choosing this
there is choice present and then you
choose whether to attend to it further
or not based on the wisdom you developed
yeah so that's when somebody who's not
free from that self-centeredness they
cannot choose to cease to be
self-centered because that will be a self-centered
because that will be a self-centered
choice they make
so they need to undermine it and how do
you undermine it by digging under and
what's basically under from where you're
standing it can be called peripheral not direct
it can be called peripheral not direct
in front of you
so that's why i use that word basically
just to give the idea to people
yeah yeah okay so if i just to back up a
bit like now yeah you
know you kind of came back to it anyway
um
when you use the word peripheral if i
understand well you can correct me
it's basically is it meaning
that it's not something that it's not an
object of your senses it's not an object
like what is what is not the
the direct object of of your attention
yeah exactly because if it becomes a
direct object of your attention then
something else is peripheral
because now what you're attending can
only be direct
as opposed to peripheral
yeah so it's not an
object of an object of your senses so or
like so it's not a sensation not
you can't be just paying attention to
sensations or sounds or
or whatever um
and when you said example that you have
to be kind of
develop the awareness on the level of
knowledge then this is on the level of like being
then this is on the level of like being
aware of the
almost being aware of the attention
itself like being
kind of well being being aware of the
peripheral of your attention what's peripheral to
of your attention what's peripheral to
that which you're attending
and that's exactly the definition of
yoni somanasikara
the only so meaning the womb of your
attention not the attention
so in the same sense and i cannot see
itself but you know that there is an eye
present for as long as there is a sight
present so it's already it's already a
peripheral relationship even within your
own senses
sense organs and sense objects so that's
the definition of yoni sumasikari is
basically not like
knowing where my attention came from in
the past or something analyzing the
roots of my attention
it's knowing presently the basis for my
current attention
a basis that cannot be attended because
if i attend to it something else is the
basis for my current attending of that which i
for my current attending of that which i
thought was the basis
so if you keep trying to to kind of uh
attend it it's like a dog chasing its
own tail
to the extent you try to reach it to
that extent the tail escapes you okay so
okay so
so you were saying about you mentioned
about actions as well about like the
intention of your actions how you can be
uh
um like have the peripheral aware like
yeah keep this does have the babies that
this is the basis of mindfulness
essentially um and this i found is interesting
um and this i found is interesting
because i
because it's kind of easier for me it's
easier to understand
than than like a body posture
because this is like if you intend like
if you intend to do something if you
have an intention of even just moving or
speaking or something
then like to be to keep the
awareness of of intention i can
understand this
easier as a as a base of mindfulness
because also because it's something that
like is really directly linked to
removing uh removing kelisa because your
uh removing kelisa because your
intentions are driven either
driven usually by by uh greed by
like aversion or by by
a moja by not knowing if i understand
well so then like being aware of the
so then like being aware of the
intention
but what i was less clear about was how
you were kind of talking of it as a
sort of like a general
background of your um
like general background of your
experience or something
um maybe i'm not remembering it well
um but as i from what i can observe and
intention is always something quite it's
more like particular it's quite specific
like you you sense that i see like right now
you you sense that i see like right now
right right right now that's not
attention this works
yeah yeah no that is a choice what
you're talking about
which is more particular but choice is
basically intentional
intention but the only reason you can
make the choice
is because you have general intentions
as possibilities
that you can choose because you can
choose to speak or be silent
you can choose to say one thing or the
other and then it becomes particular
making of the choice but that choice can
only be made because these intentions
are already given as possibilities
so that's the difference between um like
intention and intentional intention which is what
and intentional intention which is what
we commonly call a choice that's the
difference between like
um the relationship between like the
intentional mind the cheetah
and then chatana which is the actual
intention of the choice
that you make on account of the mind
they gave you these options so the
lustful mind
will lean your choices towards choices
of lust and so on
now if you have wisdom on account
towards the whole situation
that's how you can then choose to say no
which is your first step basically sense
restraint and so on
but the intention i'm talking about it's
not on the level of when you
intentionally intend to it and then make
a choice that is particular
and the only reason it can be particular
is because generally the intentions are
given and waiting to
because you can also change your choice
as well you make a choice to do
something then you change your mind
you still have the other options there
yeah and those options are not
particular they don't sit in front of
you
so when you say intention you mean like
basically the
all the possibilities of what you can do
pretty much exactly yeah
thoughts images dumbers on the level of
possibilities that's exactly what what
intentions are in that sense and that's
why you then
can choose to intend with a certain
leaning of your mind and so on and
that's when it becomes a choice
so that's you you are not responsible
for the intentions for their arising
but you're responsible for intentionally
intending them
on the basis of the last aversion or
delusion and it's those choices that then will
and it's those choices that then will
make those intentions arise more or less
for you
so a person who keeps acting out of lust
will have more options of lust
presented to him that's like even for
the first six seven years
mara was harassing the buddha hoping
he will take a bite until he realized no
his mind will never turn to this and
then he left him alone
and in many other symbols that was
described the experience of another hunt
now that these intentions suddenly the
recognitions of last
version were kind of poof just
disappeared in a second
but arahant's intentional intention of
those things
he's incapable of so eventually these
things will completely cool down
and then even as these options that he's
not responsible for
it will cease to appear like the flies
will cease to come to the
basically i don't know rotting meat if
there is no more rotting meat
left lying around the flies will fly
around a bit longer hoping for it
or crows oh yeah there was a similar in
the suttas it was the crow
like mara was like a crow seeking what
can it bite what can it pick on but it
would have provided nothing and then the
crow just left it
so the these intentionalities have just
evaporated eventually
because they haven't been maintained and
fed through these intentional intentions
of lust
aversion distraction and so on
okay so there's a point here i'm
struggling to get
get a hold of because now okay so in the
beginning you okay so we have the level of like
you okay so we have the level of like
all the possibilities of what you can do
so but this is like for everybody at any
time there's always the possibility
of let's say like
of the i don't know let's just say you
have an itch everybody can decide
whether to scratch the itch or not to
scratch the edge
like there's the both both possibilities
there then you have the
uh then you have the like
automatic decision or choice it's not
really it's automatic you decide to
scratch the itch mostly for most people
unless you are aware enough of the itch
like even if you're aware enough
beforehand to decide not to or to have the choice
to decide not to or to have the choice
that
that you see is there um
and you couldn't continue
well yeah no that's exactly it you have
you have the two choices
because you don't have any other
knowledge that's exactly why knowledge
results in liberation but if you say the
gain knowledge
that you shouldn't scratch now you have
an option to not scratch
and you have a reason as an option to
choose to
which you didn't have before
but if you develop that knowledge
sufficiently enough and stop scratching
you will heal so knowledge resulted in
liberation so it's not that these choices are
so it's not that these choices are
universally present for everyone i mean
of course
scratching nature are not scratching it
sure but what we are talking about is
the choices on the level of your mind
for greed or non-greed aversion or
greed or non-greed aversion or
non-aversion
delusion non-delusion and now
choices of greed have like myriad ways
of manifesting itself and so on
but all of them share the common nature
of being rooted in greed which is what
you keep persistently choosing
so then if you start abstaining from
that and learn that maybe greed is not
good suddenly you do recognize the choice of
suddenly you do recognize the choice of
sense restraint like sensory strength
for example
an average man today in the world he
doesn't even have that as an option
it's inconceivable for a person to be
sense restrained
by their own will it needs to be some
sort of religious practice
some sort of faith-based determination
in their mind they cannot fathom it in
any other way
but say you start actually understanding
the nature of your condition and start
seeing for yourself that scratching the itch is
for yourself that scratching the itch is
fundamentally making things worse now
you have an option that you directly see
as valuable which you did not have
before so intentions change on the basis of
so intentions change on the basis of
your knowledge and basis of your other
intent because
you chose to learn this you chose to
listen to the dharma you chose to read
the suttas
so you are responsible now for
cultivation of new intentions later on
and that's exactly what what we said
even nibana being asankata being
undetermined it's actually determined
determined by what
but one's decision to practice and
develop it back in the day
not immediately but you know when he
left the household life and so on
so the choices he made towards nibana
determined the niban eventually
resulted in
yeah so now yeah this i like to say
this i understand um
so what i was trying to allow them yeah
just i was trying to become clear on the
okay so so now you say like for again
for everybody they don't even realize
example they don't i would not say yeah most
they don't i would not say yeah most
people you don't
they don't think about or you don't
realize that you have a choice in regard
to
like in regard to what you do because
most of the time
um you're
like you're just automatically like by
by default you're driven by agree
diversion delusion
from what i can observe well it becomes
it becomes by default because people
choose to avoid responsibility
for their own choices and their own
actions that's why we always go back to
that as well
as a prerequisite for the right view for
the right mindfulness like a
pre-prerequisite is accepting
responsibility for basically your choices your
for basically your choices your
intentions your actions for everything
you feel
even if it's not your fault you need to
accept responsibility first
because they will prevent you then from
fueling ignoring the nature of yeah
of your own choice that you do choose to
make as such so uh
as such so uh
acting out of greater virgin illusion
becomes automatic because you are choosing
automatic because you are choosing
oblivion of
towards your responsibility you are
ignoring it you're turning a blind eye
that then results in automatically
following desires or scratching and
that's why then people say oh it's not
my fault i just have this
it's true it's not your fault that your
desire is automatic
but it is your fault that you ignore
responsibility in regard to that which
is what makes that desire look automatic
and the reason people ignore that
responsibility is it's unpleasant
and they don't have enough knowledge
wisdom they haven't been told enough
they haven't understood sufficiently
that actually despite being unpleasant
accepting responsibility
is beneficial for me
so they need to learn without knowledge
they will not do it
so it's a vicious circle of
automatically perpetuating that which
makes their desire
automatic
yes i mean what i was i was referring to
as well like
the fact that let's say somebody is in a
a conversation and now the
like one of the one of the people starts
i'm just going to give an example one of
the people
like sort of uh points out
to something the other one has done
wrong like
let's say you like you have uh acted it
responsibly or something like this
and now like what happens for most
people in this kind of situation because
speaking it's especially difficult like
they will automatically just want to
defend themselves like automatically
just to
reply without any without considering or
without thinking about it without
like even if even if you know like even
if you want to practice or you know that
like i am not supposed to and i don't want to
i am not supposed to and i don't want to
react in this way i don't want to like
act defensively or i don't want to
like i don't want to behave in this way
i don't want to behave like in this sort
of angry
reaction but the reaction like
the the mind makes the reaction before
you are able to
like practice restraint in it and then
people only realize afterwards like you
become sure then you have regret oh no i said
sure then you have regret oh no i said
that i shouldn't have said that
sure um so
so like in this in this sense the like
the choice of reactive the choice of
replying in a defensive way or in a kind
of angry way
this is something that because at that
at that moment there was no awareness
there there was no like
block there was nothing to like to to
stop it from arising
like the mind makes business by by
itself and then you realize afterwards
so so what i was kind of
wondering is that is like is this what
you i was wondering if this is part of what
i was wondering if this is part of what
you were referring to in the
in the scent like the difference between
like you have all the app you have the
option of not replying in that way
of not reacting defensively you do have
to
like you would have the choice but
because the but because the mind is sort of like
the but because the mind is sort of like
it just reacts automatically without you
without you being aware without you
knowing and then afterwards you realize
well yeah not quite then at that point it's
yeah not quite then at that point it's
automatically the time and as i said
the reason why it's automatic is because
you maintain the basis for that
so you want to see where the problem is
in the same sense
you know having a fever when you catch a
virus is automatic
but what if you learn how to prevent
catching a virus you won't get a fever
so having a mind move and respond even
if you don't want to and you can't catch
it in time
means we are doing something or
maintaining something
on some level that then makes that mind
overwhelmed and the very first thing
it's in the last talk we posted now it
comes down to that
whether your value is towards management
or towards uprooting
so if you think you shouldn't be saying
this you shouldn't be doing that
that's on the level of management which
as i said everybody starts like that
but really you want to see i don't want
to be affected whether i choose to speak
or not
i should not be affected emotionally but
what was said to me
and for that you are responsible and
then you realize that is the basis for
my mind
automatically blurting things out that i
shouldn't have said
i was affected so how can then i not be
affected then i don't have to worry what
mind will say
because it won't be rooted in
self-defense gratuitous or something like that which
gratuitous or something like that which
means he won't be unwholesome
that's why arahan doesn't need to worry
about his actions in a sense because he
knows whatever he chooses to do will not be
whatever he chooses to do will not be
rooted in greed aversion or distraction
or delusion
so in that sense it's not automatic
that's what i mean
mind-blowing stuff it's automatic but
you through your
other choices when you're not affected
are maintaining the basis
which then makes the mind blood things
out verbally
or for some people physically as well okay
okay
so now kind of
jumping and many jumping many subjects
but um
but yeah no i am i actually listen to
your to your last uh talk yesterday
to your last uh talk yesterday
um and and yeah like i
i i like agree with the
with the point that
[Music] okay it's not enough to just like to
okay it's not enough to just like to
become angry let's say when somebody
says something this
like points out something you have done
wrong or to and to want to defend but
even if you're kind of
able to restrain yourself not to say
it's just not good enough like it's not
good enough to
to avoid saying this i mean it would
still be better
than like saying the words and then
having regret and then having conflict
and that's another thing by the way if
the mind automatically blurts stuff
out means you haven't developed
restraints efficiently
doesn't matter how pressing whatever you
want to defend yourself against the
choice of not acting out by body by speech by
of not acting out by body by speech by
mind always remains there
the fact that you acted out the mind
said something or thought something
means you need to
develop more you need to be able to hold
it more
without actually letting in the more you
become aware of that lack
so to speak the more you'll be able to
develop it but if you think
not you specifically but if a person
might think oh
the speech happened automatically means
you will not look for an upgrade there
because you don't feel responsible for
it now see you said
oh it's automatic wasn't my fault my
fault is later or
avoiding my fault is later what i do no
it was automatic but there is a certain
basis for for mind acting automatically
bases that lacks the restraint so you
can even doesn't matter how automatic it
is
you can always choose no and that's the
restraint and then the wisdom can come out of it
and then the wisdom can come out of it
so even
even in a common sense of sense
restraint there is still something to be
done there
not necessarily i must discern this
basis and why am i affected in the first
place yeah that's all on the level of
the passing and developing wisdom but
even if you don't get any of them
you can still keep your mouth shut
literally so if you blurt out means your verbal
so if you blurt out means your verbal
restraint hasn't been strengthened
enough yeah um
yes i mean like it's still i agree it's
still your fault like if you still
if you um if you kind of blurt out words
automatically then it's still you're
you're still your fault but it's your
fault kind of in the sense that
you were not you were you were not
mindful enough and you were not
restrained enough at that at that point
and from the point of view of one who
practices that's a big fault
without fixing that fault there is no
progress so
it's not like okay i mean sure it's not
as bad as somebody who is no interest in
practice dharma but you don't want to be
comparing to that side of things
so restraint has not been developed thus
wisdom cannot arise in regard to speech
in regard to being affected by what
other people say
i cannot uproot my emotional kind of
vulnerability so to speak until i fix
this first
so that's what i mean it's not automatic
at all in a sense
like it's just a symptom for which
you're not directly responsible in in
the sense of you are not generating the
symptom but you're fully responsible for for the
but you're fully responsible for for the
reason of that symptom
yeah yeah i mean yeah when i say
automatic i kind of uh
it's a way of uh of of saying that
like even though like you don't you yeah
it's the way of saying that you kind of don't
the way of saying that you kind of don't
deliberately sort of
decide now i will speak these words
because you know that you're not
supposed to say them
yeah that's what you need to you need to
actually start kind of
fabricating and investing effort to
develop responsibility
for things that don't necessarily feel
their fault
because that's the only way to then
actually approve things correctly
and especially in regard to speech it's
um
like it's a it's an interesting point
because
like this what because we we we have
said and we both like we both agree that
you if you are if you are speaking things
if you are if you are speaking things
without considering and then you then
have regret later
then it's it means that you're doing
something wrong means that you haven't
developed enough
enough restraint in regard to your
speech and you don't have enough
mindfulness but like the kind of mindfulness that
but like the kind of mindfulness that
needs this is the point i'm trying to
come to actually is the
the type of mindfulness that needs to be
there in order to be able to practice
restraint in regards to the words that you're
in regards to the words that you're
saying obviously it can't be just about
being aware of like
the sensation of sitting on the chair or
being like
mindful of the like something outside
object of your senses
but like so from from my understanding
like you need to be
aware basically you need to be aware of
your own mind like the
of how like the
of the fact that these
like you're hearing these words and now
what happens in your mind as you hear
them like do you have the does the mind react
like do you have the does the mind react
with
the anger or not and now like if it
weren't and and now like even if it's reacting
and and now like even if it's reacting
in anger then if you are aware at that
point then you're able to stop this
but if you are not aware then you're not
able to stop it or if you're kind of
aware if you're more aware then you can
like be able to um
not allow the mind to react in anger so
how are you then
how would you then go about being aware
being aware about
being aware of your mind how would you
do that then
how would you then not not lose
awareness of your mind so then you don't
say something
out of carelessness
well if somebody is but you need to just
maintain awareness of your mind
essentially it's something that you need
to practice
no but say i don't know what awareness
of the mind is or in other words it
might mean one thing for me another
thing for you
so yeah how can i understand what
awareness of the mind is for you how can
i practically do it
i want to be aware of the mind the way
you're describing how can i go about and
do that
well it's like not to look at what you
see and what you hear not just saying
somebody is telling the is saying these
words but at that point you have to maintain
but at that point you have to maintain
awareness of who hears like what
what is hearing the
like the at that place or at that at
that point
like who is who is hearing who is
speaking who who is
who is acting or who is who is listening
like to be a like if you were aware at
that point now you know
like to know to know at the point where
the words are
where the sound example is meeting the
mind like because when somebody is
saying
so if it's about a point where the sound
meets the mind it is about things you
see in here because you started by
saying it's not about things you see in
here but if that's what you're paying
but if that's what you're paying
attention then it is about what you're
hearing
no but what i mean is not to the not
paying attention to the sound itself but
paying attention to
how it is formed in the mind like how it
is heard
the like for example because i have i
mean i cannot give many examples from my
from myself like this
well it's heard as an insult for example
i heard an insult
so i was aware of hearing the sound
entering my ears and everything else
but it was an insult
so how do i be aware of that so i'm not
insulted to begin with
but the point is that it's a it's an
insult only if you're
like it's your mind that takes it as an
insult like i am insulted
but the mind took it already so how do i
how do i not be affected by that
because everybody starts by already
being insulted affected
greedy averse and so on
so how do i then not be affected by the
insulted mind
do i analyze what i heard what do i do
no how do i be aware of it so i'm not
affected of it
with buy it sorry
expected by it doesn't matter
so let me just get your question
straight so how do you be aware of
be aware of this in the way that you're
not affected by it
yeah by the mind
because what you were describing to me
sounds like i'm hoping
you're assuming the mind is already
insulted well that's that's what i'm
trying to get to
like what you described too it's like
i'm basically trying to
set up this practice whereby i will
hopefully not get insulted
by analyzing sounds or or paying
attention to who hears
or introducing these other questions
they will sort of maybe deflate the
insult but the fact is
the people start with an unenlightened
mind with the mind that's not free from
greater version delusion which means
insult will be first lust will be first
aversion will be first
so how am i not affected in the first
place not how will i manage once i'm
affected
how will i whoever affected now learn to
not be affected by this
so okay first of all i mean i'm not
really talking about analyzing the sound
or
or something like that it's just uh on
the level of
of like awareness um
but but if you're what you're asking is
so
like if you're already affected then
they first of all if you're even if
you're already affected then at least if
you have the
if you are aware enough at the at the
point of that like if you're aware of
like being insulted that the mind that
you that your insult is
or that you that like this this uh
feeling of of being insulted is there
of of being insulted is there
then at least you can decide not to
speak based on that so sense restraint
okay so like at least then if you were aware
so like at least then if you were aware
of that point
of being being insulted then you can
decide not to speak
based on that but you have to be aware
of
like of what's going on in your mind of
the like
feeling of being an insulted letter that
is there in order to then practice
restraint or not um
okay but you can also like i mean
but if you like if you unders first of
all there's many
there's different points how do you not
become affected in the in the first
place like i would say partly partly is based
like i would say partly partly is based
on
kind of developing understanding
like understanding of the
being this is more specific but
so why then would i need to ask myself
why then would i need to ask myself
who hears and who's offended and what
did i hear
and what sound and why why is that
relevant
um no but when i say like ask who hears
it's not it's not as a kind of
question that you kind of ask yourself
or something to
to analyze it's just as a way of sort of
pointing to the place to be aware
like to to well
not looking outside at the sound
but why would that be relevant so the
sound did offend me the sound was the
problem
no the sound is not the problem the
sound is a sound this is the point like
if you
then it doesn't really matter like what
i heard and who
heard he doesn't really it's irrelevant
what matters is i'm affected
here and now doesn't matter why and who
said what and to what extent i don't
need to pay attention to
the words even in that sense
so the problem is not in those things
so how would you do that right so then
how am i aware
of where the problem is because when i
ask you do this you describe the sound
and the question and so on
i'm sure he meant different but doesn't
matter the point is even if
even if you say oh you don't really ask
a question you just look for the place
why what place is it the place that i'm
affected it means well i am already the
fact i already know that i don't need to
look for the place
so what is the problem let me put it
like that what is the problem in being
affected what is the problem in in an insult is
what is the problem in in an insult is
it the words is it the person is it the
attitude even is it my conceit or this no what is
even is it my conceit or this no what is
the problem there and then
while i'm insulted
what is the problem by being in the bay
the fact is that you feel insulted
already
what is the problem of an insult like
sometimes a person can say something to you and
a person can say something to you and
you're not insulted sometimes they say
the same thing and now you're insulted
what's the difference between the two
the will difference is because example
like you can hear the same
insulting words from in a movie example
um or like in another
context and now you will not get
insulted because it's not
because i'm not inside the same context
i'm not relating two different contexts
would which would be two different
experiences the same experience same
context same person same occasion same habit
same person same occasion same habit
once i feel insulted another occasion i
don't which is quite possible
what would be the difference between the
two it's not the words i hear
it's not even the mindset i do recognize
look he wants to insult me like
yesterday so what would be the difference then
so what would be the difference then
between the two
they're one constituted and you'll get
affected by it exactly
pain suffering unpleasantness
that you want to get rid of so you want
to be mindful you want to be aware
no need for sensations no sound no
self-questioning of the psychological
nature all of that it will be done
inevitably in the beginning but you need
to maintain the sight
like the eyes and the prize which is no
fundamentally the only reason insult torture anything
the only reason insult torture anything
is a problem
is because emotionally it's
uncomfortable and i'm habitually
resisting it
that's why i suffer not because of the
words not because who hear the words
who's offended
it's because when the experience of
disagreeable arises endures in this
five aggregates there is craving against
it
and without a knowledge of that it will
be impossible you a person will never
arrive at it
doesn't matter how much management how
much meditation techniques and
vipassanas in the colloquial sense of
the world
they do because it all revolves around
being affected already
and missing the point which means for
even to to the slightest degree you miss
that the point of insult is being
unpleasant and you resist that to that extent you
and you resist that to that extent you
will
at least implicitly assume it's the
words it's the person
it's something i've done i wasn't
mindful enough i didn't do this i didn't
have my meditation
i made all this music i will not do
those mistakes all of that is secondary
to the fact that no presence of craving
means presence of suffering not presence
of unpleasant words
unpleasant actions unpleasant thoughts
so how would you be aware of that you
realize up by recognizing where the
problem is
so mindfulness knowledge go hand in hand
you will not be able to be mindful of
these things
unless you start discerning them and you
will not be able to discern them
unless you actually hear about them in
that sense that's why the
two factors for the arising of the right
view is the right instruction
and the right yoni sumanes the proper
type of
like knowing what the attention is so to
speak because if you just hear my
actual words without the peripheral
context of your own experience to which
these words apply
you have no yawnes or basis so you're
just attending
literally taking word for word in
mantras and so on like what people
commonly do
all these i just said that that doesn't
say this and so on i read the suitors i
study suitors but
peripherally you want to discern the
context where this applies to you
here and now this very moment which is
why this very moment the roots of
suffering are being maintained by you
and that's exactly how you get even the
confidence then you you
you're not even afraid of what you will
hear in the future
what people will do to you in the future
because the place where the pain is has been
the place where the pain is has been
uprooted
which is the craving so it doesn't
really matter what comes this way
the basis of suffering is gone because
suffering was never in things that were
coming through your ears
eyes and so on not even through your
thoughts so to speak
it was in your own ignorance of
basically your own attitude towards your
own presently enduring feeling
here and now
um yeah like bay at this point about
yeah i
this point of if i can paraphrase
generally yeah that you suffer but
mainly what makes it suffering what
makes something suffering is because
you because of craving like what makes
anything suffering is because
that you like want to get rid of it or
you want
or want something you're already doing
it
i want to get rid of it i am already
trying to get rid of it that's why i
already suffer
it's not on the level of choosing or not
choosing you're already if you already
suffer if you're already affected you're
already getting rid of it
yeah and the point where there was one
point that you mentioned that
um like again
just again in regard to the same example
like hearing uh
hearing insulting words that there is a
because there's on now now you mentioned
unpleasant feeling
arises has arisen that you were trying
to get rid of and this is what makes it
painful or suffering if i got it right
um but for somebody
somebody who's got rid of craving
and that got rid of uh yeah
get rid of their self-centered point of
view let's say
how does the unpleasant feeling of being
insulted arise
how can that be possible
the insult the disagreeability of it
but they're not resisting it so it's not
about this
well the offensive attitude the
threatening attitude of the person
perception of that perception is
disagreeable of it like saying when the
buddha said
sometimes a monk asking for instruction
he gives him destruction then he goes
and does the opposite
buddha sees him doing the opposite not
being restrained
and he said the target has disagreed
with that he experienced the
disagreeable feeling
but that disagreeable feeling cannot
overwhelm his mind in other words there
is no craving in regard to
disagreeability of that perception
it's not that person who is free from
craving and arahant
has no concept anymore of people's
behavior or this is threatening this is agreeable
or this is threatening this is agreeable
this is disagreeable
no he cannot be affected by it but
agreeability and disagreeability is
still there and that's the difference
um but in the sense that yes like the
like something is
okay it's uh yeah i'm shouting
you i'm shouting i'm punching my face
i'm threatening to hit you i'm calling
you names
all of that is significant you perceive
that you know what that means
does not lose the meaning of all these
things but he loses being emotionally
overwhelmed by it
you can judge example the behavior that
behaves you can see okay if you start to
shout at me and to
threaten me and everything okay see i
can see okay this actor out of anger is
wrong like it's
immoral sort of uh like
it's a moral behavior but why would it
be
disagreeable for me like the
example or hearing hearing insulting
words is there's no reason for it to be
disagreeable for me
well there is no reason to not be
disagreeable either
you are not in a choice of of how things
arise for you
you just find things agreeing or
disagreeing cold
hot that's why the buddha compared the
words and abuse of others
to should be endured like the way you
endure the elements you endure the
insects biting you
yeah so you trying why is it that
disagreeable is basically overstepping
into the domain of nature of perception
and trying to why is it like that
doesn't matter why
only the only thing you can know and you
are responsible for
is are you resisting the disagreeable
are you fearing it
are you trying to get rid of it are you
trying to prevent it out of fear and so
on
and are you trying to prolong the
agreeable are you existentially
dependent upon agreeable
why is there disagreeable and agreeable
it's basically like asking
why the aggregate of sankara is there
why the aggregate of perception is there
that's kind of a meaningless question
because the question is the result of
the aggregate being there
but i'm not sure because in regard to
the like disagreeable things that arise from
like disagreeable things that arise from
because let's say
as let's talk about i mean a sound can
be
or like a yeah a sound can be
something that like physically is yet
hearing and hearing a sound can be sort
of physically painful for the ear like i
say a really loud
sound so it's disagreeable physically
disagreeable you don't suffer you don't
fear it but it's disagreeable
in itself yeah
it's just yeah it's felt so asking why
is it disagreeable it's like asking why
is there a sound
it's on the same footing what i was
going to say is that the
like disagreeable from from hearing
words is a bit different because that's
not something physical
it's only on the level of the how the
mind how the mind takes it like if it's uh
how the mind takes it like if it's uh
because hearing you can hear the same
words based like in like as they said like you
based like in like as they said like you
you're an insult
right well it's not a word so it's the
context that you're still hearing if you
don't hear the movie
the mind will have no context of
impersonal insult
so whichever way your mind takes it it
did it
it boils down to the sound you heard
again that's why the buddha said he
a skillful man can use heat called
instant bites abuse of others and so on
it's on the level of elements besetting
you because there is meaning even in
because there is meaning even in
meaningless sounds so to speak meaning
to the point of
disagreeability that's what it means
screeching sound
agreeability i don't it's nothing
specific there are no words to it
but it's still in its very essence it
suits or it disturbs that's it and same with
or it disturbs that's it and same with
the speech obviously speech gets more
elaborate because now there's all layers
of meaning of the words in the language
and designations
but fundamentally none of that would
exist if somebody didn't actually say it
if you didn't hear it so the sound is
there still as a basis
and fundamentally doesn't matter how
much how much it means
positively or negatively what the person
said fundamentally
it all remains bound with the sound that
you heard the words so
it's agreeable or disagreeable
fundamentally pleasing or displeasing
but just the point i was trying to make
maybe maybe doesn't matter but the but that
maybe doesn't matter but the but that
the disagreeable is not
in the sound it's not because of the
because of the nature of the sound
it's only because of the nature of the
meaning if it's if it's about words
that's where you're suffering yeah
that's the difference between suffering
on account of disagreeable
and disagree what i'm talking about and
the disagreeable i'm talking about is in
the sound
that you heard that's that's as far as
basically your responsibility goes
you can now over analyze and say it's
because they meant this so they meant
that but fundamentally none of that
would be
even there if you haven't heard it
it would not be relevant it would be
like a movie you didn't watch
[Music]
and it's quite important what i'm saying
is because
if you do divorce agreeability and
disagreeability from the perception
through your senses
it enables you then to go through the
analysis of the sound
not in an abstract sense but like who
where it came from separate the meaning
which kind of basically feels almost as
if you are dealing with the problem of
it
but you know the problem is not that
sound is agreeable or disagreeable or
neither maybe it's a neutral sound
the problem is that agreeability
disagreeability neutrality means basis for craving for
neutrality means basis for craving for
you within you
but if you if you are focusing on the
relationship between the sound and
disagreeability and why is it
disagreeable or
why it shouldn't be and the meaning and
so on means you're not dealing with the
problem is
so it doesn't matter why it's
disagreeable what matters is
is there craving against the
disagreeable experience is a whole
of somebody saying mean words to me
doesn't matter the individual syllables
the words the accent none of that is
relevant who they are is irrelevant why do they
who they are is irrelevant why do they
say this why do they want to hurt me
absolutely absolutely relevant what
relevant is the experience as a whole
is disagreeable and that's what i'm
resisting if i stop resisting the
disagreeability the actual violence cannot harm me
the actual violence cannot harm me
anymore
so how do you stop re what like what do
you mean by resist
stopping to resist the disagreeable of
it
first you need to see exactly so if you
think disagreeability is not in the
perception you have misconceived it if you think
you have misconceived it if you think
disagreeability is
equals your suffering you have
misconceived it
so you need to see disagreeability of
the experience as a whole as a risen
phenomena that you did not necessarily create and
that you did not necessarily create and
you have no say in it directly
but you are subjected to it and that's
why sense restraint needs to be done
beforehand sense restraint that prevents one's mind
sense restraint that prevents one's mind
from blaming the
sound or the person they said or some or
attacking them
implying they are the cause for my
suffering so you stop you start restraining then
so you stop you start restraining then
you still
try to analyze the disagreeable why did
i say this why did i react like that
maybe i shouldn't do it was i mindful
enough all of that revolves around the
fact that you are resisting the
disagreeable which means you're not seeing it you're
which means you're not seeing it you're
not seeing it for what it is enduring
there but if you start actually if you stop
but if you start actually if you stop
investing effort in managing the
disagreeable it's like no disagreeability is present
it's like no disagreeability is present
doesn't matter on account of what
and then refrain for as long as it takes
from jumping into the management of the
disagreeable then you get to see that
all you have is disagreeable
disagreeability or agreeability and your
attitude towards it that's the that's
basically the core that's the only
relevance here
that's the gateway for any suffering for
any last for any version they will then
be manifested
are you welcoming the agreeable are you
resisting the disagreeable as a
preemptive attitude pretty much as a
view and the only way you can see the view in
and the only way you can see the view in
regard to agreeability or
disagreeability is to first start seeing
agreeability or disagreeability
correctly that's where the buddha
himself said
all i'm teaching is suffering like
correctly people don't even know what suffering is
people don't even know what suffering is
all i'm teaching is dukkha
and freedom so i'm actually teaching you
dukkha like the buddha would say means people
like the buddha would say means people
like can suffer
the utmost the greatest misfortune and
still completely have no idea what the
actual dukkha is so dukkha and freedom
from dukkha
agreeability and freedom from
agreeability disagreeability
freedom from disagreeability but it
needs to be seen for what it is
because even when you have the view that
but disagreeability doesn't feel like
it's in the words
all of that you have pretty much
developed inferred maintained
on account of experiencing the
disagreeable words
first and then your mind your thinking
took you into explaining that it's not
in the words and so on
because it was first and it remained
first so
it doesn't matter as i said whether it's
in this so this
point is experience as a whole of
certain words in this particular
instance felt disagreeable and it was a problem
felt disagreeable and it was a problem
for me and that's why you gave in to all
these reflections basically revolving
around trying to to get rid of it trying to
trying to to get rid of it trying to
free yourself from it
yeah but i agree like this is not this
is useless like to kind of analyze
after the event is uh like you're too
late like that you
already already was disagreeable it was
already a
problem and now you say oh it was only
because of the was only
it was only because of the meaning it
was not because of the words yeah that
is useless
um yeah there's a
say agreed um
[Music]
and then um as
like a bear related point what i've
because right now we're talking about
agreeable and disagreeable but
in and and like feeling
feeling suffering on account of that
but what i'm
[Music] like i would say that also like you can
like i would say that also like you can
talk about it on that level but i mean
there is the kind of additional problem
let's say in getting
angry about something is it one is that
it's like one is that it's disagreeable but i
like one is that it's disagreeable but i
think most people
like as a normal person when you get
angry you don't even kind of
notice that it's disagreeable because
you're so focusing on the
object of it the anger itself you don't
see it as disagreeable
sure i mean the problem with anger is is
is is more that it's in like unwholesome
that it's wrong that it's
that it's not that it's not good
so like from that point of view
like you need to learn to you need to
learn to not be
to not get angry in the first place okay
but
like if you kind of if you are getting
if you are getting angry already
then like if you're getting angry and
then kind of saying it's not
if you if you allow yourself to get
angry and to continue to get angry and
to speak out of anger
like in your aim yet your aim can be to
not get angry in the first place but i
would say
you kind of have to start by first not
allowing yourself to
not not allowing the anger to continue
without allowing anything
you need to start restraining yourself
first you're not going to see things on the
you're not going to see things on the
level of your mind if you if your
physical and verbal actions are not
restrained beforehand so
you have to stop acting out of anger you
have to stop acting out of lust
with the goal of not being affected by
it in the first place
so if you're still affected by the first
place not acting
well restrained but affected in the
first place
you still have a massive problem there
that's the route yeah
and it doesn't matter if you're getting
affected as much
or i'm not getting affected as much no
nature of being affected is something
i'm still susceptible to
thus it's still the massive problem
because often what happens when people
get into practice they
they start cultivating the environment
that suits them which is fine
but then they become they start to
depend on that environment
whereby you will have a protected
environment well you might be the senior
monk nobody will be challenging you
offending you questioning you nothing
really to poke you around
so you don't really have this anger
arising anymore because now you're
basically the lord of the land everybody is your
the lord of the land everybody is your
servant so to speak so but that doesn't
mean you dealt with it
so that's why the buddha would say so
you then ask yourself okay i'm not
experiencing any current angle but
can the other reason anger arise for me
if you have no idea means yes you got
your answer
so and that should be regarded as the
root of the problem not the fact that
most of my time i'm not lustful most of
my time i'm not angry
that's because of the circumstances or
because you're in another hand which one
is it
so if a person is honest they'll know
the answer
but no often often it's regarded as oh
dhamma helps me i don't get angry as
much are you still liable to anger yes that's
are you still liable to anger yes that's
not the dhamma that's just your
management on account of how you took dhamma to be
on account of how you took dhamma to be
to be but dhamma actually will uproot it
means you will be incapable of anger
yeah they reminded me of that story with
the mistress veda i think another one the
mistress veda i think another one the
the maid servant the
mistress was supposed to be so patient
and so kind
she was testing her yeah
so see i mean that yeah that's
why i was a it's it's like it's a good
point it's true like this i mean i was
wondering even um
because i'm not a monk and i don't i'm
not or none and
like we don't we don't live like that so
um
so it's kind of interesting uh
intro kind of interesting way of
practicing here that you like you have kind of
here that you like you have kind of
plenty of
opportunity to see this to see that like
anger can arise or like the that these
these things can arise you're not in
sort of a position where you
when you're never being confronted by
anybody so
in one sense i would say that's almost a
useful thing because you have to kind of
be confronted by the by the fact in a
way exactly
i think if it can be it can be
beneficial for people but that's again
that's another
place where peripheral awareness
whichever whichever way we want to call
it would be handy
would actually like result in knowledge
if people's practice is about current
sensations in present moment present
moment present moment
presently i have no lust presently i
have no ill will that's it that's my
concern present moment no future present moment
present moment no future present moment
should be your concern
ana reason lost can it arise oh
oh yeah that's another present moment
that i'm obviously ignoring because i'm
so absorbed
in present sensations and and present
breathing and presently being here
and now you know judgment free or
whatever else
you know people psychologize okay that's
fine great so
the environment is suitable you made
some effort
are you liable to lust are you liable to
aversion oh and if you are you are presently
oh and if you are you are presently
liable
ironically enough so you're so absorbed
in the present moment that you don't see
your present liability to the very
things you you think you're overcoming
and that's what like see the possibility
of future lust
it's not present there so you cannot
attend to it that's exactly
why people have people who are used to
this kind of practice of just
just what's in front have problem
understanding why you only someone is
the way we describe it
cannot grasp peripheral because if the
moment they think it they make it in the
front but it is there
a possibility of future lust it's
exactly that see it's an intention
that persists there because you're not
free from lust
arahant has no possibility of future
lust no intentions of lust gone uprooted
no intentions of lust gone uprooted
because he has made the effort on that
on that
right level understood it
okay but yeah this was a this was a
point in the video yesterday that i
wanted to ask about anyway so um like
when you say
the possibility of future like the yeah
the possibility of future lust or future
possibility of future lust or future
sexual desire or future anger
uh like yeah it's it is there as a
possibility and it
is a problem which means that a
possibility of future lust
means its current liability
and that's a problem
but it basically means that you haven't
uprooted it like as long as
it's there because you have not reported
it yeah you haven't actually
yeah you haven't fixed the problem so
everything else that's around you like
oh most of the time i'm not angry most
of the time i'm not lustful
that's all circumstantial it should be
regarded as such for as long as you
don't approach it
that's the true freedom but many people
by just focusing on what's in front
what's in front is that i don't get
lustful don't get angry
oh i must be free then or something but
until you get lustful or angry then you
quickly deal with it
and then you say well most of the time
i'm fine
but if you're honest you would see up
being liable to it that's where the
problem is rooted so am i free from that
or not
if not means most of the time
circumstances suit me and they don't
challenge me if they were to change
my mind would be overwhelmed by those
things that i basically
think i uprooted
and you don't want to wait for that to
tell you to happen because it would be
too late to deal with it
yeah i mean like yeah i see that it's
like it's it's a useful
it can be like it's a useful thing to
like ask yourself or to put this kind of
pressure on yourself to
um see okay even if i'm not getting
angry right now i can get angry
it's not it's not optional it's complete
it's absolutely it's the only gateway
towards right uprooting
everything else is management even if
all you do is read the suitors
and and and practice unless it's done
through this gateway of liability
to dukkha one way or the other it's
going to be on the level of management
um okay but the but the question i had
was about
like why do you
because i mean is dukkhan not present
anyway now in your current experience
if you are like because it's it's
present is it not present anyway like why do you
is it not present anyway like why do you
need to think about the liability for it
in the future
because that's what dukkha is dukkha
uneasiness this is that's what it is
liability i mean the divine messenger the buddha
i mean the divine messenger the buddha
wasn't sick wasn't old
and wasn't dead but he recognized his
inevitability so if he just focused on whether it was
so if he just focused on whether it was
present he wouldn't have seen those
things as divine messages
so you need even wisdom to recognize
where the problem is let alone to begin
dealing with it
then the sense that yeah exactly
you are liable to suffering yeah the
fact that you're liable to suffering
if you recognize the liability currently
it's currently unpleasant
so actually dukkha is present for
everyone who's not free from it
from that liability it's just that it's
not seen hence the buddha teaches dukkha
first and then freedom from it most people
and then freedom from it most people
won't even see their liability as a
problem
i mean yeah like when you pay attention
to the
idea that you are um
that you're subject to suffering this
isn't unpleasant or this can be this can
be unpleasant
that is it is unpleasant
but if you don't pay attention to the
idea of the fact
that you can that you will suffer that
you will get all that you will get sick
that you will die
you don't pay attention to that then you
don't feel that it's suffering
yeah that's why you need to start paying
attention to it because it is your
reality it's unavoidable
you can choose to not pay attention to
things that are avoidable
but it's unwise thing to not pay
attention to things that are unavoidable
the divine messengers i mean yeah if you
don't pay attention to sight sound smell
taste touches
they bother you they'll stop bothering
you the fact is you can be bothered
and you will be bothered first so you
choosing to not pay attention is you
choosing to ignore the problem
i mean if you if you don't accept that
you are ill you'll think you're healthy
yeah and that is pretty much
the common world's sort of way of
dealing with a problem
just ignore it just ignore the problem
it's not there don't pay attention to it
absorb yourself with your nostrils or
sores of feet or where the chair touches
you or something don't pay attention to
your current liability of your existence
because it's just too overwhelming
and what do you mean exactly by like
paying attention
i mean you have that you can have the
idea that i will suffer in the future
okay so
like then and like i remember you um
and said in the video yesterday like you
don't need to keep
you don't need to keep paying attention
to the idea and keep paying it well
you need to keep paying attention to
that idea if
if the mind is liable to like just
ignore the problem
but once you become aware of the problem
you start feeling that
concern that dukkha then you don't have
to keep paying attention to it in the
same sense of
oh am i like because now you feel it
that you are liable and you already know
so
what you feel becomes pretty much the
the exemplification of your knowledge of
your situation
and that's exactly what i said if a
person does feel dukkha correctly there
are only two possible outcomes
madness or noble search there is no
third possibility
if duke is seen correctly mind will
either go mad if he cannot deal with it
or if he has enough composure it will
seek how do i uproot this
how do i uproot this
and most people never even allow that
choice to manifest even the ones they
commit to the practice of dharma and so
on
it's all done on the level of management
of the current disturbances
not on the level of uprooting my
fundamental liability
sickness aging death [Music] um
so i'm just trying to um
like yeah so in the beginning you from
from the beginning you need to recognize
that you're
that that's yeah that you that you need
to recognize yeah this is like to get the
the
to start practicing from the beginning
with the right attitude
it should be this like you have to know
that you are sick in order to go see the
doctor to
like otherwise yeah if you if you don't
know that you are sick if you don't feel
that you are sick
you don't go to you don't go don't go to
see the doctor
um but like what is still not
that clear for me is like the
because then i mean they then you start
to then you have to start to practice
right so like what i'm trying to
understand is
what the practice is like what is the
what the practice is
yeah it's yeah well if you start living
if you start living within the
recognition of your pretty much
perpetual liability to do
pray to suffering as we would say
and not give in to like psychologizing
managing trying to explain it to
yourself so you don't suffer as much
you will then abandon that which is
basically liable
to that to that suffering so you would
then and that's where this
this all the other talks we did on the
sense of ownership and nietzsche seeing
correctly that's where it applies
not on the level of explanation of the
world is after oh yes
the modern science has said everything
is impermanent in the buddha he said
see modern science and dharma is the
same no first you need to feel
that existential liability and then
recognize that a nature and then give up
that because of which you suffer
give up your self-centeredness give up
the dependence on pleasure
all the padawans that would have talked
about but only
on the basis of that framework of i am
liable and this
needs to be uprooted
because otherwise if you take it when
you say if you don't take it on that
basis sorry if you don't take it on that
basis it will be taken through the
attitude of management of the
disturbance of suffering
not the approaching of the liability to it
yeah i mean like what i was talking
about was more about
the um and like i i
like i agree like you're trying to just
managing and not kind of uh not have
things that are disagreeable to you
is uh like in order not to be not too
yeah not not to like suffer so much or
not to it it's no use i mean example
that like you will always just try to
get away from the things that are
disagreeable but you won't
like uh you won't try to remove the
things that are agreeable
yeah so the management i'm referring to
is not it's not necessarily
it's not like a choice or people choose
i will manage
it's basically the yeah the the default
result if you're not operating within
if you're not operating within
the liability the recognition of
liability to suffering
if you're not operating within framework
of that existential anxiety
you are managing your suffering even
unknowingly things you do will be on the level of
things you do will be on the level of
management not uprooting it because
you have well either have no recognition
or have fallen from the recognition of
that general
anxious nature of your situation
anees this is not dukkha or this is
bothering me
that's all secondary to it yeah
yeah because i mean if it's only when
something is bothering you then it's
very easy you can just try to find the
you people you put yourself
people you put yourself
the problem is not that people haven't
heard enough of dhamma or
haven't read enough of the suitors the
problem is that
pretty much none of them like all the
people that practice but without
actual becoming arahants and so on means
something's wrong there
and it's not that there was lack of
teachings or lack of suitors or buddhist
instruction or that it's not clear
enough is that they never ever heard or learned
is that they never ever heard or learned
on what level it needs to be applied and
it was always stayed within the
framework of management unknowingly so that's what
of management unknowingly so that's what
i mean
you have to stay within that recognition
of that liability pray to suffering
which is
pretty much the framework of anxiety
so that's why people would go mad if
they stay on that level and often would
like or quickly manage it because yeah they
or quickly manage it because yeah they
don't know any other way
so you need to sense restrained virtue
is what will prevent you from going
mental
um okay so there's two things now you
said here um you said that
sense restraint and like morality is for
what prevents you from going mental
and you said this [Music]
it would prevent you going mad on
account of anxiety you will not approve
the anxiety
yeah then you can include it eventually
yeah and to put in like basically from
from if i if i understand well like if
you if you to practice correctly
if you want if you practice directly and
then you have to be always practicing
with a view basically to the
aim of of getting
out of suffering yeah like this has to
be the aim constantly
and everything should drive you towards
him yeah yeah
like this this is what i this is what i
understand like that you have to
like this is your the aim should be
always at every moment
and it's not like get out exactly but
it's not
it's not an abstract aim in a sense it's
not like i must keep this thought in my
mind it's it's the anxious aim it's the aim
it's it's the anxious aim it's the aim
you feel
anxiety remains there liable to it
the aim is there outlined you don't need
to think it anymore in that sense
what's my aim what is my aim but unless
you have uncovered that liability of
that's anxious in its nature then you
have to drill and drill
until you learn what dukkha is first
yeah so the way at first like well about
like making this aim
clear and then taking your actions in
order to bring
taking every action or taking every
practice in order to bring you closer to
this aim
this is correct the same clear about
um then feeling like
do you mean that you should have to feel
anxious constantly
in practicing or no well you don't have
to be like
sort of trying to contrive anxiety but
if you're thinking correctly you will
feel uneasy to what extent
that uneasiness will be a threatening
anxiety and fear or not depends to what
extent you basically developed your seal
and are able to hold it
but the recognition of the peril is
i mean part of understanding the danger
is part of freeing yourself from
sensuality from the world from the aggregates from
from the world from the aggregates from
everything so the danger is still there
arahant sees it
but yes how dangerous that danger is for
you it's basically how how much you have
it's basically how how much you have
understood it or not
but it's still the same danger so
initially it's probably going to be very
frightening and very anxious but if you don't act
and very anxious but if you don't act
out of it
don't break the cellar sense restraint
and that strength that you've
accumulated to basically controlling
your output of your behavior
then you can actually well you you will
be able like
anxiety is a problem when it's
threatening when you when there is a
risk of being overwhelmed by it
if you have sustained it long enough if
there is less and less
risk for that danger to overwhelm you
but you and then you get to see it even
clearer ah the peril the danger becomes apparent
ah the peril the danger becomes apparent
and when the danger is apparent you have
abandoned any passion there was that
which is dangerous
so to me it's completely not abstract or
on the level of theories of figuring it
out it's actually
felt the danger is felt first and then
you not being liable to that same danger
is also felt which is when other danger
becomes apparent
thus the freedom becomes apparent from
it
so how much you're gonna feel anxiety
and when
in what process depends pretty much on
how much samadhi who have developed
how well your virtue has been
established and how intense
is your current recognition of samadhi
of sorry of anxiety of liability to
suffering sometimes will be more sometimes so you
sometimes will be more sometimes so you
have good days bad days
but that is that is the the field where
you have to do the work
it's not optional that's what i'm saying
how much you're going to suffer on
account of these options that's what
we're going to say
for some monks practice is pleasant with
pleasant results
painful with pleasant results and so on
but it's the same thing it's not like oh
i have this approach or that approach
it's just
some minds are stronger they will suffer
less on account of the threat
because they have more composure samadhi
some minds are not that strong so
they'll suffer more that's what exari
put the
who practiced through vipassana not
samadhi as much his way was unpleasant
and long but then yeah he was
the second to the buddha in terms of the
foremost wisdom
but if you start actually practicing
rightly even the unpleasant way you will
recognize the liberating aspect of it so
you will have no problem
in basically enduring that anxiety it
doesn't matter how big it gets and how
threatening it is
but in order to get there you need to
start rightly and that
will be hard for somebody who hasn't
been practicing on that level
so they just if i so to understand well
what you're saying you say that
you have to like you have to feel
anxious feel anxiety feel suffering
feel the suffering uh in the sense that
you are
that you were like
that you have no control over your over
your life and that you will get old and
that you will get sick and that you will
die no matter what you do and
all of this um so you have to start like
start from this point
in order to have like the in order to
like keep the have the aim and then keep the
keep the have the aim and then keep the
aim of keep the right context
as a basis for the correct direction of
your practice yeah
and that's that's what i mean that's why
people don't keep that right context not
because they choose something it's because they
they choose something it's because they
don't want to feel that discomfort
because they didn't have enough
information no it's existentially
avoiding the recognition that you are within the
the recognition that you are within the
parallel situation
without any means of escape and that's
very frightening
that's essentially fear of death in the
nutshell all the people are not necessarily even
all the people are not necessarily even
might call it their way or be aware of it
um can you hear me now
sure oops okay
okay um
so yeah so just cut there a little bit
the last part i heard was
that you were saying how when people
like start by the on the wrong start on
the wrong footing essentially or they
don't practice
rightly it's because of um
basically because of ignoring ignoring
this fact this ignore yeah ignoring
your which means you can always fix you
can always fix your footing at any given
time you can always fix that you can always
you can always fix that you can always
restart and re-establish the right
framework but the thing is the more you give in to
but the thing is the more you give in to
ignoring it because it's fundamentally
frightening and unpleasant
the more you drift away and more
incapable of accepting it
you are because the more you the more
effort in trying to have run it you
invest it
so theoretically anybody can become an
arahat in any stage of life but
practically if you spend 20 30 years
more avoiding this and even
practicing while avoiding it it will be
virtually impossible for you after all
that invested effort
to basically just wipe your slate clean
and re-accept that fundamental liability
that will fill you with anxiety and make
you like back onto the day one
i mean people won't do that in for
mundane things let alone for something
so
profound and hard to uproot such as you
know existential anxiety fear yeah
yeah i mean that's why i think most
people they don't really practice with
the with the for that for the aim of the of
with the for that for the aim of the of
the
of the goal really they don't they don't
you practice for another reason or for
like wanting to
like basically wanting to feel better or
to and if they don't practice with that
as a basis the right basis they don't
practice dhamma even if it's the dhamma
they're doing
i mean the buddha said himself only like
he
the his teaching has only one taste like
the ocean has only one taste of salt
taste freedom from suffering nothing
else so
suffering freedom from it is the only
place where dharma can be
so to me it's not optional it's not oh
let me choose this or choose that
it's the only way yeah um
there was maybe just one more i i'm
aware of taking up a lot of your
your time already um
[Music] and
i would just like to maybe to ask on one
more one more point
there or two the
so like if i can kind of samurai is
basically the
like overall the the different points
that are mentioned
um
so from the beginning you have to start
like with
uh recognizing that you're sick like the
recognizing that you that you're
what the nature of your problem is and
then you have to like make the aim
clear it be like if you're not
practicing with the realization that
you're sick and
like we needing to be healed yeah then
you're not
right you have to resist the temptation
to manage the symptoms
at the expense of the recognition of
your illness that's still there even if
you remove the symptoms
yeah but am i still alive yeah thus i'm
still ill
so don't get complacent even when things
don't bother you
and certainly don't make your practice
revolve around dealing with things that
bother you only
yeah yeah so i mean don't look just for
a painkiller basically like you want to
go to the you you want to go to see that
go to a doctor
if the pain is too much take the
painkiller but don't forget that
fundamentally the only reason you needed
to take the painkiller and
the head pain is because you're still
sick there's still the underlying
illness
yeah and as long as you haven't cured
the underlying illness then
you can you can continue to take
painkillers but the illness is still
there and it's getting worse
exactly and now you don't even have the
symptoms to tell you how worse it is
yeah yeah exactly so it's a
it's a big problem i agree like
because you can feel so calm like you
can you can make yourself feel very calm
by just like
concentrating on the breath or something
like that and you can spend hours a day
just concentrating on
a sensation of breathing and now you
feel so much better and you think
everything's going so much better
you think you're fine now you stop like
searching for
a way out because you think you're fine
yeah that's that's what i said in other
talks like most of
like today's meditation buddhist
meditation practice it's just calming
techniques which is fine if you need to calm down
which is fine if you need to calm down
but don't confuse that for somebody
they will result in pania and complete
wisdom and liberation
and then like the other point is then
about like what
what is the like once you once you know
what you're what you're doing then what
does the practice consist of at one
point you said
morality is to stop yourself from going
mad um
i don't know if i have seen
this uh like
i think morality is essential like it's
a essential base of
of practicing morality is in the sense
of like no not
having any wrongdoing in in thoughts
words or actions
[Music] and
and then you pay what you were what you
were talking about what you were saying
is that basically you
um you need to kind of realize
that the problem like understand where
the problem is in the sense that you
um that you can become affected by
anger that you can become that you
become greedy or that you believe that
you are or having
are or having
desire for things in the first place and
not to just like want to
kind of manage these things when they
arise so this point is
okay um
and yeah so then the and then the
correct practice
like to what yeah what kind of still is
like i'm
kind of trying to figure it out is the
if you're if you're practicing rightly
like if you if you
if you practice if you if you practice
correctly
then you should see that you're
practicing correctly right so there's no
need to have the same
anxiety of um that was there in the
beginning if you know that you're
practicing rightly
yeah if you're not so see you're not
ignoring your liability to suffer you're
not ignoring the peril you're not turning a
ignoring the peril you're not turning a
blind eye you're not distracting
yourself from it and
it doesn't bother you as much not
because you pretend it's not there
because it you get used to it
anxiety will stop bothering you when you
get used to it
i mean you are able to maintain
composure in the face of it
and the only way to do that is to train
composure in the face of anxiety
and to come back just to just come back
into the beginning about
the because we were telling the base of
like the base of being able to practice
uh mindfulness correctly is to have the
um the right kind of awareness to be
able to
have awareness correctly which um
is not about just uh like paying
attention to sensation or paying
attention to sound or paying attention
to something else nor is it about
like analyzing your thoughts or
analyzing your uh like experience
your uh like experience
and so now you were um
so now you said the periphery meaning
the [Music]
[Music]
like what you said was the basis for
that for on which you're paying
attention periphery means the first
the background the background of
whatever it's currently attended in
there so
the the the mind is the background in
itself the intentionality the possibilities as
the intentionality the possibilities as
as we described that's already the
background in itself
so it's that's that's what peripheral is
okay it can sound technical and i think
in those videos we use it for the sake
of the context but it's really
the background of your currently engaged
experience that you don't want to make into a
that you don't want to make into a
foreground because then again
the point is not what is the foreground
or what is the background the point is
to be aware of the background
while there is whatever action intention
presently enduring feeling and so on in
the foreground
and that background is literally the
knowledge of that situation nothing else
no sensations no no nothing specific
that's why it's so hard to see because
it's non-specific
and what else is non-specific what the
nature of things
is non-specific the nature of this
specific cup the nature of this specific object
cup the nature of this specific object
is non-specific from the point of view
of the specific object
to which that object kind of pertains to
and that's that's in essence dumber the
nature of things
so it's always found in that background
where the knowledge is
so that's what i mean oh specifically
there is not where the knowledge is
yeah where the knowledge is what you
just said like where's the yeah
specifically there is an insult angry
voice everything all of that is quite specific
everything all of that is quite specific
not specifically
there is a presence of suffering that
i'm resisting
non-specifically there is discomfort
there are many
different non-specific ways you can take
but it will be the same nature of this
experience so
fundamentally the problem here is not
what's being said what's being heard
not even what's being felt yeah the
problem is that
within this basically experience as a
whole i'm resisting it and i
have a view that i should not suffer
that i'm in control and i should not
suffer that's all implicit
that's the nature of that experience
that is the background that is the
the vessel in which you and that's where
you get you get insulted
when you hear something immediately
because the framework
ready for insult is already there in
other words
framework ready to resist any form of
discomfort that comes through the senses
is already there currently maintained by you you
you